so this is Madame nicaya hundred and
fifty to the Nagas now good riddance
some tribe of people 150 150
thus have I heard on one occasion the
blessed one was wandering the coastal
and country with a large chunk of
bhikkhus and eventually arrived to this
coastal and village named Naga revita
and so the brahmin householders of their
village heard that the buddha had come
and thoughts now it is good to see such
our hands so they went to visit him when
the Brahmans householders went to visit
the Blessed One Sun paid homage to him
others exchange greetings sat down some
extended their hands in salutation some
were silenced and so on when they were
seated the Blessed one sitting said to
them he addressed them householders if
Wanderers of other sticks sex asks you
dozens of other priests or other
religious ascetics so amongst
householders what kind of ascetics and
brahmins should not be honored respected
revered and venerated you should answer
them thus those recluse and brahmins who
are not rid of lust hate and delusion
regarding forms cognizable cognizable by
the eye so on for the other senses whose
minds are not inwardly peaceful and who
conduct themselves now right idli now
unrighteously in body speech and mind such recluses
in body speech and mind such recluses
and brahmins should not be honored
respected revered and venerated why is
that because we ourselves are not rid of
lust and hate and delusion regarding
forms carnival by the eye our minds are
not inwardly peaceful and we conduct
ourselves now righteously now
unrighteously embodies version of
movements since we do not see any higher
righteous conduct on the part of those
good refuse and Brahmins they should not
be honored and
spected revered and venerated that's
what the Buddha says they should God
thinks
but householders if wonders of other
sects asks you thus household what kind
of recluse should be honored respected
and revered you should say those
recluses and brahmins for rid of lust
hate delusion regarding forms cognizable
Bala I whose minds are inwardly peaceful
and who conduct themselves righteously
in body speech and mind such recluses
and brahmins should be honored respected
revered venerated why is that because we
ourselves are not root of last hate and
delusion our minds are not inwardly
peaceful and we conduct ourselves now
righteously now unrighteously embodies
speech in mind since we see higher
righteous conduct on the part of those
good vertices and brahmins they should
be honored respected and revered
and then he asked householders if
wonders of other sects asks you thus but
what are your reasons and what is your
evidence regarding those Venable buttons
whereby you say about them surely these
venerable ones are here the rid of lust
or practicing for the removal of lust
they are either rid of hate or are
practicing for the removal of hate that
either rid of delusion or are practising
for the removal of delusion being asked
us you should answer those Wanderers and
thus it is because those venerable ones
resort to remote jungle thicket resting
places in the forest just what you well
what would you prove because you don't
know those people
so why would you assume that they are
free of these things well because the
opposite of remote jungle dwellings is
that which is founded in greed aversion
delusion people inhabited areas access
and accessibility obviously to
sensuality to this wealth to create a
version delusion maybe they're not
seeking sensuality not seeking anything
a basic version but it clearly seeking
distraction well why else would you come
to people to glue to village what would
you as you know sort of they can take a
resting place if you come you come for a
purpose alarms rounds or something but
otherwise why would you go into the
inhabited area it's absolutely no reason
for it and that there is a good criteria
then the those who want to see what
those people are practicing for can use
ok so he prefers he prefers to stay in
the remote dwelling in the forest with
our beasts and then to come with people
no because he has issues with people it
hate him but that's what he finds
restful when we see him is normal lucky
no okay yeah yeah yeah of course gonna
see me he's a nutter or something sure
yeah but no if this case says the
criteria is the buddha says no you would
prefer that so the only two reasons why
he was somebody would prefer that he
moved and I mean likely mode I don't
mean like you're gonna stay in a
monastery people you need to get your
own room
you're still crowded by people even if
nobody comes to room you're still with
people so if somebody goes it stays in
the wilderness then and that person will
prefer that for two reasons as the
Buddha said one they are already either
free from greed aversion delusion or
they're practicing for it which means
non solitude is directly contradictory
for practice of diversion delusion it's
incompatible with it so if somebody says
oh yes I'm practicing for believers
delusion he lives surrounded by 2030
other people and most of the day spends
in the community of people they don't
they're not practicing for that no
matter what they think they're not
practicing for dreamdry diversion
delusion because for that solitary based
is necessary because they like what most
of the day you are actually alone
literally alone alone and maybe once or
twice a day you come together for
whatever purpose whether it's bender but
or some some meeting or something but
most of the time you are alone and not
for a week or two weeks I mean even
though it's better than nothing but no
that's your mode of living do you prefer
because as householders they said they
would say well how is this ascetic
living well he lives in a you know very
good house I mentioned that he's
surrounded by ten twenty thirty people
sure like servants yeah he's got many duties
like servants yeah he's got many duties
many Judas many engagements so buddy but
he he he does live in harmony with all
those people just like I wish to do in
my community sure in my village I too
would like a big house I too would like
to have all sorts of food available for
me sure yeah you know buffet they'll be
great yeah
so this ascetic is living the life that
I want to live as a householder yes so
that that's the thing like then you sort
of me at most it's a it's a slight
upgrade to a hostel life say like a
commune life spiritual communists that
upgrade because well it would be a
slight upgrade if say they were to keep
the rules came in keep the increases so
it's a slight upgrade to a house full
bath because of the eight precepts but
it's not a necessity as in a household
that can start keeping the increases and
you already met that so that's what it
means that if you if you kind of review
and see like well actually no I add
something to that sometimes I don t know
righteously no exactly so now I can I
can leave I would only to do the
treatment there wouldn't be a difference between
there wouldn't be a difference between
me and this is communal i venerate you
just wouldn't because there is another
higher distinction everything else and
then you many other regards it's
actually easier in my life so what if I
were to then keep doing precepts and now
we have a relatively is your life but of
course many people who not trade that
many people are afraid to be celibate
and so on but that's that's just the
state of present age but the point is it
you need to recognize okay so it's a
slight improvement just because I'm so
bad as in I can't even keep the Five
Precepts or eight reasons sometimes I do
sometimes they do which means okay so
and yet sure enough these people in the
community sometimes they don't sometimes
they leave sometimes they come back so
what's the like non worldly distinction
except the circum
and there would be freedom from greed
aversion delusion they will be pretty
Nibbana and practicing towards a partner
and again so how would you set that
criteria how do those people income your
live if it's a confident means it's a
community means they don't live there is
no seclusion or seclusion is relative to
the to the comin together mostly it's
about coming together occasionally
you'll get time off but again that's
like a household life occasionally you
know I own well now I can go and afford
attending holiday on my own what are you
treat so if a householder to review his
situation is well this is not a massive
improvement it's not gonna result in
freedom from greed aversion delusion
because there is no there is no
remoteness there is no literally that
being alone most of the time and it's
not incidental it could be alone is the
hardest thing to do for the petitioner
that's so the Buddha said you have to
develop wisdom in order to start finding
pleasure in solitude otherwise it's
going to be painful that's the whole
point that's why the neutral feeling if
it's unknown if it's not understood it's
unpleasant and that's that's the
definition of border starts neutral but
you don't understand it you don't
understand the feeling you want
something whatever you're craving is
there means that neutral feeling it's
going to be very unpleasant very
unpleasant if you stay with it and
that's why so see that's the problem
that I they were often kind of go back
to when I described this thing like with
with his group retreats organizer treats
the people perfectly silent nothing no
engagement no distraction but you're
still with other people and then your
meditation technique because something
becomes something you do something you
perform so you're not alone being alone
means having nothing to do or very
little to the eternal day except sit
with yourself and with your own thoughts
and with your own feelings
so it's not incidental that all the co2
Jenner's effort revolver on avoiding
this even the petitioners were committed
to practicing Buddhist teaching yet live
in massive communes constantly
frequenting people cause of the spending
time with people coming together in the
morning coming to get any afternoon
coming together in the evening to teach
do you look at you there's loads of
stuff to do
oh go for retreats will you I must do
step one step two step three watching
watching moving breathing breathing I
must do this I'm gonna do this because
if I stop doing anything I will start
sinking and that's why people terrified
of Solitude even those who go and seek
solitude they then have to find
something they must do in it so they
don't sink in that solitude and for as
long as you rely on search efforts you
are not the one it's delighting in
finding joy in solitude so that's why
you have to stop doing that take the hit
of the anxiety or whatever else even at
the risk of going mad just as the Buddha
said sometimes someone is in promise
they set off the swing correctly to the
other Shore but then they drown so you
want to prepare yourself with your
burner - the truth will set don't go to
forest unless your virtue has been
properly developed the teaching has been
understood and so on but then there
doesn't mean like okay so I feel
justified you're not seeking seclusion
because I still have what are you
waiting for
it's a you either way and everything is
summed up in that little passage is
probably many people would have just
read okay of course yeah yeah yeah
there's like no but if you again what
the Buddha says there that kind of
dwelling means freedom from greed and
delusion or practice towards it absence
of that kind of dwelling means not
practicing no matter what you put any
post another important thing is see when
people who do go seek seclusion then
they have to resist that inner kind of
impulse to find the work in
I must meditate on this and then the
meditation technique becomes a
distraction from being alone with
themselves experience no you want to be
you in that solitude and start sweet
feeling that solid you basically
following you threatening you
that's what virtue is not negotiable you
need to develop urge before I because
then you can take it you can take that
threat because it's only a threat
nothing can happen to you unless you
choose to do it that's like a definition
how crazy there are people who would do
things break down I see the danger you
see you fishing but come nothing can be
done to you unless things you choose to
do with yourself on account of that
pressure I come to that fear and that's
that suit of the fear and dread where
the Buddha would go into this remote
dangerous running with like tigers and
what I'm doing walking meditation at
night and he said well if while I was
walking back and forth on drink on the
Dhamma I fear would arise because he
heard something in the bushes he
wouldn't change the posture until the
fear is dispel that's exactly what I'm
talking about
he wouldn't do anything on account of
the reason fear until the fear is
dispelled then whatever he does won't be
rooted in trying to avoid the fear so
that's why me
you you can't go mad unless you give in
to you can't do anything unwholesome
unless you give in to the pressure can't
do anything to you unless you let it
unless you choose to allow it so the
Buddha wouldn't do until this disappears
so that it doesn't become up this was
letting in the pressure nothing in the
fear then if he were seated or standing
while the federals he would not change
the posture means his basis of
situation would not change you would not
do anything significant until the fear
is dispelled or subside and then you
will do it just to make sure that it's
not rooted in trying to avoid it but all
these things will become a permit for
the one who goes then starts well
seeking solitude if they're not ready
for it
then every single effort should be
towards preparation for it
virtue restraint knowledge of the
teachings and then okay so I'm gonna
show you what must what must I do by
these non activity and start emulating
it right start seeing yourself as
completely circumstantial and so on and
you can used to see don't break down if
you don't break the pieces if you don't
run away if you don't suddenly jump on
of you say no no no no this is a mistake
you should go and be with people people
are good basically if you don't give in
in any shape or form you will get used
to it and then you start mercy and
that's what the Buddha said if I
understood that so that's that's the
other suit it says among who who was
basically living in the company living
in the common so to speak living with
others and he obviously values it finds
finds it peaceful finds it finds it
delightful finds it contentful to live
like that that he will be developed
pleasure of seclusion that's not
possible and for the monk who lives in
the company who because of that cannot
develop pleasure seclusion that he would
then develop sign of his mind discern
the sign of the mind that's impossible
the one cannot discern the sign of the
mind because he doesn't live in
seclusion because he delights in company
that he will then develop the right view
that's impossible
and then without a right view to know
basically what damage that's impossible
we don't know
to develop Nibbana that's also
impossible oh because he delights in
company oh because he's never dealt with
his personal solitude for himself and I
don't mean he pushed himself for ten
days you know not talking to I'm not
seeing anybody
just son no actually found the joining
and start preferring it not done it as a
novelty kind of little little to whine
himself up with something like some some
intense retreat no actually found the
joy in it and it starts to prefer it and
in order for a person to do that they
need to go through that that layer of
anxiety and feel being alone without
having anything to do and so on but that
is that is the gateway since if somebody
does that and they'll start finding the
pleasure in solitude if somebody starts
finding pleasure in solitude they'll
start to discern the peripheral signs of
their own mind as a phenomenon not their
own doing
if one start discerning the peripheral
signs of their own mind he can develop a
right view and become sort of fun
because he knows you got that's where
the practice is that's where the suit is
apply that's what all the things that we
talk to I should be discerned he sees
the area where he sees the domain
basically of it but without going
through that personal terror of anxiety
of boredom to arrive in it that's not
possible and all of that is rooted in
company or rooted in seclusion
hence such a categorical criteria if
they seek such dwellings they're either
like that or practicing for the freedom
of that they don't they're not like that
and not practicing freedom from that
oh yeah that's it again so even the sort
upon us will I play people back in the
day they dealt with that personal
existential pressure of solitude boredom
without resorting to meditation
technique without resorted to wrong
movie now resorting to company without
resorting to distractions they dealt
with it they've seen it they understood
it then they chose maybe to not practice
and went back because then Judas would
have a laugh but that's a completely
different topic that can be discussed
elsewhere but even they did not like he
was in the middle of his sort of
household life and suddenly don't know
they dealt with it you don't hear about
it the suitors but you hear about it
there where the Buddha talks about the
right view what's necessary in seclusion
is not delighting this was a work it's a
real question that there's a certain
fear and death now say no because he's
right view involves understanding yes
exactly but he fears the dying that's
whatever whatever existential anxiety
boredom and being alone that's that's
what death is that's what people are
terrified of death because because
that's what people are terrified of for
them as well you start losing their mind
no more people perfectly functional
people you lock them alone without any
or put them in some remote dwelling with
like on their own even if it's exactly
what because that's where the beginning
is understanding that nature of that
which is understand the nature of death
understand the nature of neutral feel
the delight in ethology
it's all the same thing and so the
burner that's why he often said if he
doesn't become an honor he might become
in the moment of death because the
direction of that is the direction of
the right view is the direction of
dispassion disenchantment letting go is
the direction of the burner
that's what petitioner fears Nibbana
from the digital point of view Nibbana
is closer to death then too but the
traditional things Nibbana is because
the true piece true absence of suffering
is when you really wish your life what
is still alive
but it's the dying part side if yeah
yeah the bangs set for somebody who
hasn't understood death is there but you
understood death means you're not
subject to death that's right for
another the word death is never used in
the suitors he was used like his
aggregates with breaking bad that's why
the many many of people who come in here
the Buddha would like get get shocked
terror in anxiety and you know
figuratively start pulling their hair or
maybe literally fall on the ground be
their breath or they will kill us your
teaching will destroy me because yeah
from somebody who is not relinquished in
the self of you but the Buddha teaches
is the destruction of the self you
obviously to be extinguished not through
the actual destruction of it because it
was a mistake to begin with but petition
doesn't know that so for him for him
Nibbana his death basically when he sees
it he feels it and that's why that solid
sure the Buddha said you need to get
gaining wisdom first restraint sense
restraint virtue and then wisdom to
start finding solitude pleasurable
correctly because it comes out of their
wisdom it's completely opposite of your
entire experience over to general going
with the sense is going to be the gray
let's go back to it why they they think
why they should think that someone's
worthy of respect Amana it is because
those venable ones resort to remote
jungle resting places in the first up an
uninhabited firsts for there are no
forms cognizable by the eye they're of a
kind that they could look at and
delighting there are no sounds
cognizable by the ear live of a kind
that they could listen to in the
lighting or smells or tastes or touches
of a kind that they could touch and
delight in these are reasons this is our
evidence whereby we say about those
vendor ones surely these venerable ones
are either rid of lust hate and division
or practicing for the removal see how
much okay of course yet the entire the
entire existential dread and suffering
need for company need for something to
do dependence on something to keep it
flowing base floating so you don't sink
in yourself it's all in there and that's
exactly what that that criteria is
rooted in if the person is in the
environment it's supposed that he's not
practicing for free no comment if the
person is in environment that doesn't
support any distraction any any any
sensuality any any things that you could
delight in then he's practicing for it
because I was sure we'll be spending
time in there yes we would come and he
believed he would but yet he's there
full
so person needs to learn how to be alone
with oneself or will overcome the
anxiety that comes from it pressure
border the fear not do anything to
compromise the virtue and then the size
of the mind will begin to manifest
there's no other gateway by the way
something fun is just one way the Buddha
said the reason for the review is the
reason is the presence of the side of
the mind this one side of the mind said
this is the the side of the mind can be
discerned without having went through
that day's essential solitude that's
impossible someone say well that's the introverts
someone say well that's the introverts
way but is the extroverts way community
the introduction of things to tears I
mean the Buddha told off a noble Sangha
basically a Honda was there probably
arahants you know he wasn't just with
random villages it was a group of monks
probably many of them ordered
enlightened or released so the banners
and they were sewing robes for the
Catena and discussing and doing things
preparing in the Buddha walked in and
said what is this what is his crowd here
and he says our Lord we are sewing a
rose for the Catena you know which is a
suspicious occasion they said well I
thought he was like a band of fishermen
selling their product on the market and
then he told him off for just dwelling
in company even for seemingly good
reasons to ordinance see for events and
then noble noble Sangha was reprimanded
for dwelling in company what is to be
said of two gems because they could
still theoretically their company once
you get the right view you could still
it theoretically obviously much Slover
you will progress much slower but you
still could progress because you go the
criteria you went through the negligence
of Solitude
but let let let alone those could never
even start who from the start say no
that's a wrong direction
you must stay together and that's
exactly why they stay together that's
the whole emphasis on the communes and
group and group this in rubies so people
will not sink in themselves but without
the risk of sinking how can you learn to
swim without learning to swim
how can you cross the shore that's
simply not possible
so yeah the risk of sinking is real but
then the rewards of of course in the
show are equally real as in instruments
so is the fear of sinking gonna prevent
you from ever trying to practice correct
you're already sinking kinda well
exactly that's what I'm getting it
exactly you ask yourself well okay I
might not like to try to swim because I
might sink but I'll stay on this Shore
drown drown anyway yeah so really you
don't really have much to lose of course
you don't be foolish about it as I said
virtue needs to be developed before I
said whether said himself that you you
go to the forest Wellington and they
want and be physically secluded don't
just try and jump - no okay yeah now
suddenly shut everything down low-key
and just run into the mountain well you
know that survived but not seeing that
that is your task well that's probably
the worst view you can have no no no I
don't need to know this is fine and then
space around them in fifty people where
there is a householder is funny I'm good
at the household arena in a common